

Zhengchun Liu

Senior Machine Learning Scientist, PhD

🔁 lzhengchun.github.io github.com/lzhengchun in linkedin.com/in/liuzhengchun

Zhengchun has 10+ years of experience conducting research and development around Data, Artificial Intelligence and High Performance Computing system. Currently, he is on sabbatical leave from Argonne National Laboratory and works as a Senior Machine Learning Scientist at AWS AI Labs. Specifically, he works at the intersection of machine learning and large scale distributed systems towards cloud-based Autonomous Data Warehouse.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Senior Applied Scientist

Aug. 2022 — present

San Francisco Bay Area, California, U.S.A.

- Machine Learning Scientist II

Aug. 2022 — Feb. 2023

Al Labs, Amazon Web Service (AWS) Tech Lead of Machine Learning for Al-driven Autonomous Data Warehouse.

· Machine Learning for large scale, distributed data systems.

Computer Scientist (Tenured)

Aug. 2019 — Aug. 2022

Data Science and Learning division, Argonne National Laboratory

Illinois, U.S.A. Sep. 2022 — present

- on Sabbatical leave - Assistant Computer Scientist

Aug. 2019 — May 2022

Artificial Intelligence for Science.

HPC/Systems for Artificial Intelligence applications.

Data and Machine Learning for HPC System(characterize, predict and optimize).

Research Scientist

Mar. 2018 — Aug. 2019 Chicago, Illinois, U.S.A.

Computation Institute, University of Chicago

Methods for distributed and autonomous management of the systems.

• Performance modeling and characterization of high performance computing system.

Postdoctoral researcher

Sep. 2016 — Mar. 2018

Mathematics and Computer Science division, Argonne National Laboratory

Illinois, U.S.A.

High performance file transfer over wide-area network.

Modeling and Simulation to explain the behavior of scientific workflows over a distributed infrastructure.

ENGINEERING EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer (Part-time)

May 2010 — Jun. 2013

China

Xi'an FengLiTong Electronic

Board Support Package development for μ C/OS-II real-time operating system.

Developed a backend communication service for million-level vehicle-data-recorders (IoT).

Founder

Sep. 2010 — Jul. 2013

China

Embedded System Technology Consulting & Outsourcing LLC 10+ cases, three prototypes went into mass production.

SELECTED AWARDS, GRANTS & HONORS

- Best Paper award at XLOOP'21, FGCS'21, MLN'19, MLN'18, and TRIDENTCOM'18 $\times 5$	2021, 2019, 2018
• Impact Argonne award for notable achievement in Innovation $\times 2$	May 2020, July 2022
• Top Winner of the first Technology Challenge at SC'19	Nov. 2019
Pacesetter award by Argonne National Laboratory	Jan. 2019
 Extraordinary Doctorate Award by Autonomous University of Barcelona 	Jun. 2018
$\bullet \ \ {\tt National \ Scholarship\ by\ Ministry\ of\ Education,\ China\ (award\ to\ 0.2\%\ of\ outstanding\ undergraduates)}$	×2 2008, 2009

EDUCATION

•	PhD., Computer Science, Autonomous University of Barcelona, Spain	Jul. 2016
•	MSc., Guidance, Navigation and Control, Northwestern Polytechnical University, China	Apr. 2013
•	BSc., Aircraft Manufacturing Engineering, Northwestern Polytechnical University, China	Jun. 2010

ACTIVITIES

- Professional Membership: Association for Computing Machinery (ACM).
- Editorship: Journal of Future Generation Computer Systems (FGCS), 2020-2023, Impact Factor: 7.2.
- Workshop Co-Chair: SRMPDS 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020; Al-Science'19.
- Technical Program Committee: ICDS'19; DAAC'17-19; DLS'19; ICDCS'20; SC'20; HPCC'20; HiPC'22; SC'23; IPDPS'23,24.
- Journal Reviewer: MDPI Sensors; Elsevier FGCS, JOCS; IEEE Access, TPDS.

Papers on Machine Learning and Systems

- 1. **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Michael E. Papka, Ian Foster. *FreeTrain: A Framework to Utilize Unused Supercomputer Nodes for Training Neural Networks*. IEEE/ACM International Symposium in Cluster, Cloud, and Grid Computing (CCGrid'23).
- 2. Ahsan Ali*, Hemant Sharma, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Peter Kenesei, Dennis Trujillo, Antonino Miceli, Ian Foster, Ryan Coffee, Jana Thayer, **Zhengchun Liu**. *fairDMS: Rapid Model Training by Data and Model Reuse*. 2022 IEEE International Conference on Cluster Computing. arXiv:2204.09805
- 3. Tirthak Patel, Devesh Tiwari, Raj Kettimuthu, William Allcock, Paul Rich and **Zhengchun Liu**. *What does Inter-Cluster Job Submission and Execution Behavior Reveal to Us?*. 2022 IEEE International Conference on Cluster Computing.
- 4. Jakob R. Elias, Ryan Chard, Maksim Levental, **Zhengchun Liu**, Ian Foster, Santanu Chaudhuri. **Real-Time Streaming and Event-driven Control of Scientific Experiments**. arXiv:2205.01476
- 5. Rafael Vescovi, Ryan Chard, Nickolaus Saint, Ben Blaiszik, Jim Pruyne, Tekin Bicer, Alex Lavens, **Zhengchun Liu**, Michael E. Papka, Suresh Narayanan, Nicholas Schwarz, Kyle Chard, Ian Foster. *Linking Scientific Instruments and HPC: Patterns, Technologies, Experiences*. Patterns(2022). arXiv:2204.05128
- 6. Joaquin Chung, Wojciech Zacherek, AJ Wisniewski, **Zhengchun Liu**, Tekin Bicer, Rajkumar Kettimuthu and Ian Foster. **SciStream: Architecture and Toolkit for Data Streaming between Federated Science Instruments**. ACM HPDC'2022.
- 7. **Zhengchun Liu**, Ahsan Ali*, Peter Kenesei, Antonino Miceli, Hemant Sharma, Nicholas Schwarz, Dennis Trujillo, Hyunseung Yoo, Ryan Coffee, Ryan Herbst, Jana Thayer, Chun Hong Yoon, Ian Foster. **Bridge Data Center AI Systems with Edge Computing for Actionable Information Retrieval**. XLOOP@SC'21. **Best Paper Awarded**.
- 8. **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Joaquin Chung, Rachana Ananthakrishnan, Michael Link, Ian Foster. **Design and Evaluation of a Simple Data Interface for Efficient Data Transfer Across Diverse Storage**. ACM Transactions on Modeling and Performance Evaluation of Computing Systems, 2021 Vol. 6, No.1.
- 9. Papadimitriou, George, Cong Wang, Karan Vahi, Rafael Ferreir da Silva, Anirban Mandal, **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajiv Mayania, Mats Rynge, Mariam Kiran, Vickie E. Lynch, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Ewa Deelman, Jeffrey S. Vetter, Ian Foster. *End-to-End Online Performance Data Capture and Analysis for Scientific Workflows*. Future Generation Computer Systems, Vol. 117, 2021, Pages 387-400, *2021 Best Paper Award*.
- 10. Tirthak Patel, **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Paul Rich, Bill Allcock, Devesh Tiwari. **Job Characteristics on Large-Scale Systems: Long-Term Analysis, Quantification, and Implications**. The International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC'20).
- 11. **Zhengchun Liu**, Ryan Lewis*, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Kevin Harms, Philip Carns, Nageswara Rao, Ian Foster and Michael Papka. *Characterization and Identification of HPC Applications at Leadership Computing Facility*. International Conference on Supercomputing (ICS'20).
- 12. Yuanlai Liu^{*}, **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Nageswara Rao, Zizhong Chen and Ian Foster. **Data transfer between** scientific facilities bottleneck analysis, insights and optimizations. IEEE/ACM International Symposium in Cluster, Cloud, and Grid Computing (CCGrid'19).
- 13. **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Prasanna Balaprakash, Nageswara S. V. Rao and Ian Foster. **Building a Wide-Area Data Transfer Performance Predictor: An Empirical Study**. International Conference on Machine Learning for Networking (MLN'18).
- 14. **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Ian Foster, Peter H. Beckman. *Towards a Smart Data Transfer Node*. Future Generation Computer Systems, 2018(89), Pages 10—18.
- 15. Rajkumar Kettimuthu, **Zhengchun Liu**, David Wheeler, Ian Foster, Katrin Heitmann, Franck Cappello. *Transferring a Petabyte in a Day*. Future Generation Computer Systems, 2018(88).
- 16. **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Ian Foster and Yuanlai Liu. *A comprehensive study of wide area data movement at a scientific computing facility*. IEEE 38th International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (SNTA@ICDCS'18).
- 17. Rajkumar Kettimuthu, **Zhengchun Liu**, Ian Foster, Peter H. Beckman, Alex Sim, John Wu, Wei-keng Liao, Qiao Kang, Ankit Agrawal, and Alok Choudhary. 2018. *Toward Autonomic Science Infrastructure: Architecture, Limitations, and Open Issues*. The 1st Autonomous Infrastructure for Science workshop (Al-Science@HPDC'18).
- 18. **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Ian Foster and Nageswara S.V. Rao. *Cross-geography Scientific Data Transfer Trends and User Behavior Patterns*. International Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC'18).
- 19. **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Sven Leyffer, Prashant Palkar and Ian Foster. *A mathematical programming and simulation based framework to evaluate cyberinfrastructure design choices*. IEEE International Conference on eScience.
- 20. **Zhengchun Liu**, Prasanna Balaprakash, Rajkumar Kettimuthu and Ian Foster. *Explaining Wide Area Data Transfer Performance*. International Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC'17), 167-178.

Papers on AI/HPC for Science

- Anakha V Babu, Tao Zhou, Saugat Kandel, Tekin Bicer, Zhengchun Liu, William Judge, Daniel J Ching, Yi Jiang, Sinisa Veseli, Steven Henke, Ryan Chard, Yudong Yao, Ekaterina Sirazitdinova, Geetika Gupta, Martin V Holt, Ian T Foster, Antonino Miceli and Mathew J Cherukara. *Deep Learning at the Edge Enables Real-time Streaming Ptychographic Imaging*. Nature Communications 14, 7059 (2023).
- 2. Lipeng Wan, Jieyang Chen, Xin Liang, Ana Gainaru, Qian Gong, Qing Liu, Ben Whitney, Joy Arulraj, **Zhengchun Liu**, Ian Foster, Scott Klasky. *RAPIDS: Reconciling Availability, Accuracy, and Performance in Managing Geo-Distributed Scientific Data*. International Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC'23).
- 3. Petro Junior Milan, Hongqian Rong, Craig Michaud, Naoufal Layad, **Zhengchun Liu**, Ryan Coffee. *Enabling real-time adaptation of machine learning models at x-ray Free Electron Laser facilities with high-speed training optimized computational hardware*. Frontiers in Physics, Volume 10 2022.
- 4. Mike Kraus, Naoufal Layad, **Zhengchun Liu**, Ryan Coffee. **EdgeAI: Machine learning via direct attached accelerator for streaming data processing at high shot rate x-ray free-electron lasers**. Frontiers in Physics, Volume 10 2022.
- 5. **Zhengchun Liu**, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Ian Foster. *Masked Sinogram Model with Transformer for ill-Posed Computed Tomography Reconstruction: a Preliminary Study*. arXiv:2209.01356
- 6. **Zhengchun Liu**, Hemant Sharma, Jun-Sang Park, Peter Kenesei, Antonino Miceli, Jonathan Almer, Rajkumar Kettimuthu and Ian Foster. *BraqqNN: Fast X-ray Braqq Peak Analysis Using Deep Learning*. IUCrJ, Vol. 9, No. 1, 2022.
- 7. Aniket Tekawade, **Zhengchun Liu**, Peter Kenesei, Tekin Bicer, Francesco De Carlo, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Ian Foster. **3D Autoencoders For Feature Extraction In X-ray Tomography**. 2021 IEEE International Conference on Image Processing.
- 8. Jiali Wang, **Zhengchun Liu**, Ian Foster, Won Chang, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Rao Kotamarthi. *Fast and accurate learned multiresolution dynamical downscaling for precipitation*. journal of Geoscientific Model Development.
- 9. Selin Aslan, **Zhengchun Liu**, Viktor Nikitin, Tekin Bicer, Sven Leyffer, Doga Gursoy. *Joint Ptycho-Tomography with Deep Generative Priors*. Machine Learning Science and Technology, 2021, Vol. 2, No.4
- 10. Ziling Wu*, Tekin Bicer, **Zhengchun Liu**, Vincent De Andrade, Yunhui Zhu, Ian T. Foster. **Deep Learning-based Low-dose Tomography Reconstruction with Hybrid-dose Measurements**. AI4S@SC'20.
- 11. **Zhengchun Liu**, Tekin Bicer, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Doga Gursoy, Francesco De Carlo and Ian Foster. *TomoGAN: Low-Dose Synchrotron X-Ray Tomography with Generative Adversarial Networks*. Optical Society of America A, 2020, Vol. 37, No. 2.
- 12. Vibhatha Abeykoon*, **Zhengchun Liu**, Tekin Bicer, Rajkumar Kettimuthu, Geoffrey Fox and Ian Foster. **Scientific Image Restoration Anywhere**. XLOOP @SC'19.
- 13. **Zhengchun Liu**, Tekin Bicer, Rajkumar Kettimuthu and Ian Foster. *Deep Learning Accelerated Light Source Experiments*. IEEE/ACM Deep Learning on Supercomputers DLS@SC'19.
- 14. **Zhengchun Liu**, Dolores Rexachs, Francisco Epelde, and Emilio Luque. *A simulation and optimization based method for calibrating agent-based emergency department models under data scarcity*. Computers & Industrial Engineering, 2017.
- 15. Xueping Zhu, **Zhengchun Liu** and Jun Yang. *Model of Collaborative UAV Swarm Toward Coordination and Control Mechanisms Study*. 2015 International Conference on Computational Science (ICCS'15), Vol 51, 493-502.
- 16. **Zhengchun Liu**, Eduardo Cabrera, Manel Taboada, Francisco Epelde, Dolores Rexachs and Emilio Luque. **Quantitative Evaluation of Decision Effects in the Management of Emergency Department Problems**. International Conference on Computational Science (ICCS'15), Vol 51, Pages 433-442.
- 17. **Zhengchun Liu**, Eduardo Cabrera, Dolores Rexachs and Emilio Luque. *A Generalized Agent-Based Model to Simulate Emergency Departments*. The 6th International Conference on Advances in System Simulation (SIMUL'14).

- Last updated on January 2, 2024